Yes,
דף Daf is נ"ה, Nun Heh, we start a little bit behind
on נ"ד עמוד ב'. Nun Dalet Amud Bet. תא
שמע, Ta Shma, we had just seen a whole debate taking off
on the question about whether you measure the flour based on what
you have in front of you. So if you use an amount
of yeast does it affect the measurement, I mean amount of sourdough.
We get into a large a more general debate about whether you
measure things based on the way they originally were or the way
they are now with רבא Raba trying to limit the debate and
saying it's impossible that you would go by the size what now
if it's too small, I mean you know you need to have
the right size right now, רבא Raba said that, excuse me, and
also insisting that this
the size now is not sufficient, it would need to have had
that status to begin with and trying to limit the debate only
to what happens if in the interim it shrinks and grows again.
But now the גמרא Gemara is going to continue and try to
once again more generalize the debate. So let's take a look. תא
שמע, Ta Shma, it's about a third of the way down on
נ"ד עמוד ב', Nun Dalet Amud Bet, ten lines down, line starts
with the word תיובתא. Tiyufta. Okay, תא שמע, Ta Shma,
come in here. תורמין תאנים על הגרוגרות במנין. Tormin Te'einim al ha-Grogrot
be-Minyan. Now, תאנים Te'einim are figs, גרוגרות Grogrot are dried figs, and
the purpose as we'll find out a little bit later today that
they would dry them, in addition to taste maybe some people like
it sort of like prunes versus plums, although you know most people
I assume prefer plums to prunes, but the benefit is that if
it's dried it can store for a long time and especially in
a non-age of refrigeration that's a pretty important thing. Okay, so they
would very often make their dates into these dried dates. Now, dried
dates take up a lot less space than then plums, I'm not
plums, excuse me, than non-dried
dates. Okay, so when you're coming to do תרומה Truma and you
have all of your dates and some of them are dried and
some of them are not, how are you going to measure? And
you want to do תרומה Truma from the
dried figs, right?
Figs. I've been saying dates, I'm sorry. I think at the beginning
I said figs and then I shifted to dates. I don't remember.
Anyway, thank you. Okay, for some reason in my mind I sometimes
mix those two up. Okay, so I'm sorry about that, you are
right. Right, right, you're right, no, no, no, תמר Tamar is date,
I don't know why I was saying, right, dried figs. Right, right,
I don't know, yeah right, I don't know why I was saying
that, I'm sorry. Okay, erase, go back, erase everything. Okay, back to
the point. Okay, I think I said figs initially but then I
slipped up.
1/10th, they take 1 from 100, what's the difference?
Okay, okay, so let's talk. So you've got now figs, thank you.
You've got your dried figs and your non-dried figs. Now you are
if you took, you know, from dried to dried and non-dried to
non-dried, it's not but you want to take from your dried figs
to your non-dried figs. Here's the question. Okay, right now there are
it would take if you were going by volume, which is sort
of the assumption you're going here in terms of תרומה Truma or
not תרומה, Truma, excuse me, מעשר, Ma'aser, right? You want to know
what is a tenth? If you were to go by volume not
weight, if you were to go by volume, so you would need
let's say you have 100
non-dried figs, 100 normal figs, you would need probably about 20 dried
figs
to be the volume of 10 of non-dried figs, because the dried
figs take up less space. Okay, so if you were to go
by volume you were going to need 20. Of course that's a
little funny because we all know that these 20 started off as
non-dried figs and 10 actually represent 10 percent. So that is the
question. Do you go with what it is now, do you go
with what it used to be? Now here of course it's a
little bit different because it's a different a more interesting case because
in the past it wasn't you didn't have to make it relative
to something else. Meaning here you've got some stuff that's the way
it always was, some stuff that transformed, you know, and how
are you going to sort of look at them combined? Like can
even if you were to normally say we go by just the
way it presents itself right now, but vis-a-vis something that's that hasn't
changed, that's the way it originally was, maybe we have to look
at it in the context of the way these things originally were.
I wonder why we're going by volume instead of by number.
Well, that well we are going to well the assumption is that
מעשר Ma'aser requires volume. The question here is, right you take 10
percent of what? Of the volume, of the number? No, you don't
ever say by the number. But you say it by no, actually,
you do say it by מעשר בהמה, Ma'aser Behemah, you're obviously can't
but in general you don't say it by the number. Like if
I'm taking מעשר Ma'aser for example about my olives or my wheat,
am I counting them? No, you're not. You're doing מעשר, Ma'aser, the
assumption is you do מעשר Ma'aser by volume, not by number. Okay,
so the question is here, here's a volume obviously different, but they
it wouldn't be 10 percent, it would be 10 percent if you
were to look back at the way it used to be.
Okay. Like in terms of the דאורייתא? D'Oraita?
No, because you're not, for some reason you want to give presumably
as we're going to see later on, if there's not a כהן
Kohen immediately available then there's a מצוה Mitzvah to take give him
from מעשר Ma'aser from something that has longer that has greater longevity,
that will stay longer. Okay, so you're going to give him the
so you're going to give him these the dried figs and you're
going to keep your figs for yourself. Let's take a look. תא
שמע, Ta Shma, תורמין תאנים על
הגרוגרות במנין. Tormin Te'einim al ha-Grogrot be-Minyan. You can take for the
now here I'm sorry it's the reverse also of what I was
saying. You take from the non-dried figs on the dried figs and
you go by the number. Okay, you don't go by the volume.
Alright? Which again makes sense because that's representing the proportions that it
originally was. secondly what? It's not just a question of how I
look at this object by itself, but I'm trying to figure out
what proportion it represents from this larger whole. Okay, so here it
says you take it by the current number. אי אמרת בשלמא לכמות
שהן משערינן או לכמות
שהיו, Ee amrat bishlama lekamoshehen misha'arinan o lekamoshehayu, if we look at
the way things used to be, שפיר, shapir, then it makes sense,
right? Because then these things used to be תאנים, te'einim, and then
the taking from by the number would represent a legitimate 10%. אלא
אי אמרת כמות שהן, Ela ee amrat kamoshehen,
but if you go by way you determine things by the way
they are right now, so how can you take ten תאנים te'einim
for over on a hundred גרוגרות? grogrot? If ten תאנים te'einim is
a much greater than 10% of the volume of a hundred גרוגרות,
grogrot, so how can you do this? הוי ליה מרבה
במעשר. Havei leh marbe bema'aser. You're taking too much מעשר, ma'aser, right?
Do everybody get this? If you're taking ten תאנים te'einim on a
hundred גרוגרות, grogrot, that's much more than 10% of the volume. So
if you actually just look at things the way they present themselves
now and מעשר ma'aser is defined by volume, you're taking too much
מעשר. ma'aser. והתניא, Vehatanya, המרבה במעשר פירותיו מתוקנים ומעשרותיו
מקולקלים. Hamarbe bema'aser peirotav metukanim uma'aserotav mekulkalim. If you take too much
מעשר, ma'aser, it's true you fixed the fruit, because now they've had
10% taken from them, but your מעשר ma'aser is mixed up. Your
מעשר ma'aser is not correct. Your מעשר ma'aser has מעשר ma'aser with
חולין chullin mixed together in it.
What's the problem with that?
Well, it's that that in itself is not the worst thing, except
it could mess up the לוי Levi for תרומת מעשר terumat ma'aser
maybe. But okay, you're right, that's a lot worse a lot less
worse than the reverse. Okay, anyway it's certainly not ideal. אלא, Ela,
so okay, so therefore you're not go up if you're taking if
you're taking the ten תאנים te'einim for a hundred גרוגרות, grogrot, then
clearly you're not looking at the way it is now, you're looking
at the way it used to be. אלא מאי, Ela mai, so
what do you want to say? לכמות שהיו, lekamoshehayu, we go we
look at what the way it used to be. So therefore ten
תאנים te'einim over a hundred גרוגרות grogrot is essentially ten תאנים te'einim
for a hundred תאנים te'einim and that makes sense. But one minute,
אימא סיפא, Eima seifa, look at the end of that, the end
of that ברייתא. braita.
גרוגרות על תאנים, Grogrot al te'einim, if you're taking the dried
figs for the non-dried, גרוגרות grogrot on the תאנים, te'einim, so again
how do you take it? במידה. bemida. Now that you do it
by measure, by volume, not by number. Okay, now that's strange because
you should think that in either way you look at it the
way as if they were all figs and not dried and you
take your normal 10%. So there too if you're taking תאנים, te'einim,
you should take
ten גרוגרות grogrot for a hundred תאנים te'einim and that would represent
an honest 10% of the way it used to be. Okay, so
why do we there go by measure? So אי אמרת בשלמא כמות
שהן, Ee amrat bishlama kamoshehen, if you go by the way it
is right now, שפיר, shapir, I understand why you go by measure
because you go by 10% of the volume now, even if that's
going to mean having to take a lot more of these dried
dried figs. אלא אי אמרת לכמות שהיו, Ela ee amrat lekamoshehayu, but
if it's the way it used to be, מרבה במעשר הוה, marbe
bema'aser havei, you're taking too much מעשר, ma'aser, right? If you take
if you're taking your גרוגרות, grogrot, your dried figs on the figs,
and if you were to determine based on the way it used
to be, you would just take you know ten dried figs for
a hundred figs. But if you have to take by measure, you're
going to wind up taking you know 20 dried figs because that'll
represent the same volume as ten not-dried. So you're taking too much
מעשר. ma'aser. So this whole thing doesn't make sense, right? Why when
you do one way do you go by number and the other
way you go by measurement, right? One way represents the way it
used to be, the other way represents the way it is. What's
the rule here? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says let's take a
look, so the גמרא Gemara says אלא ela you're right. This is
really this is very problematic how it keeps on reversing. הכא בתרומה
גדולה עסקינן. Hacha biteruma gedola askinan. ורישא בעין יפה וסיפא
בעין יפה. Vereisha be'ayin yafa veseifa be'ayin yafa. Notice the phrase was
תורמין. tormin. So תורמין tormin is תרומה. teruma. We translated it to
mean מעשר ma'aser because or else why would you have to have
the whole discussion. תרומה teruma you have a lot of latitude how
much you can take. מעשר ma'aser is supposed to be exactly 10%.
תרומה teruma the תורה Torah doesn't say how much. So the רבנן
Rabbanan set general guidelines, ideally 2%. You could do a little bit
more, you could do a little bit less, but there's no particular
exact amount. So he says you know what you're right, we're not
talking here about מעשר, ma'aser, we're talking about תרומה. teruma. So if
we're talking about תרומה, teruma, what we're saying is we're asking you
if you're a normal person that normally gives 2% of תרומה. teruma.
But you know what it really doesn't matter, unless you give more
either way it works. You normally give 2%, we're going to ask
you when it comes to this situation to always measure the 2%
in a way that means you're giving more. You know, so if
you're giving of תאנים te'einim on גרוגרות, grogrot, so don't so in
that type of a case, you know, give based on the number.
That way you'll give a full תאנים, te'einim, ten תאנים te'einim for
a hundred גרוגרות. grogrot. That'll be more than if you did it
by volume. In the reverse, if you're giving גרוגרות grogrot on תאנים,
te'einim, we're going to ask you to give by volume, not by
number, and then you'll wind up giving 20 גרוגרות grogrot for a
hundred תאנים te'einim and not 20 excuse me we're back to תרומה,
teruma, whatever it is, more than 2% you wind up giving 3%
because because you're using the more generous measure. So the גמרא Gemara
says you're right, this doesn't make any sense, either go by the
way it is or the way it was, how can you keep
on mixing it? So it says what? The common denominator is we're
asking you always to use the measure that's going to wind up
meaning you're giving more. So we're going to say we're not talking
about מעשר, ma'aser, we're talking about
תרומה. teruma.
Either way, you're going to use the way of measuring that's going
to wind up giving more. So he says, the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, אי הכי אימא סיפא, ee hachi eima seifa, look at
the very end of this ברייתא. braita. אמר רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי,
Amar Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yosi, רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi
Yosi said, אבא, Aba, when my father would do this, היה נוטל
עשר גרוגרות שבמקצועה, haya notel eser grogerot sheb'miktzoa, he would take ten
of the dried figs in the מקצועה. miktzoa. The מקצועה miktzoa was
whatever instrument they used to dry the figs and to process the
figs. So he would take ten of the dried figs על תשעים
שבכלכלה al tishim shebakalkala for ninety figs in the basket, unprocessed figs.
So here he's saying he would take ten over ninety and he's
basically saying you go by the number.
What's clear is it's מעשר. ma'aser. He's talking about you take ten
for the remaining ninety. Okay, so you see we're not talking about
תרומה, trumah, we're talking about מעשר. ma'aser. Okay, and he's going by
the way it used to be, even though ten now is a
lesser volume, it's less than ten percent, but it represents what used
to be ten percent.
Okay, so you see the תנא קמא, tanna kamma, about how they
measure,
by the, no, that's hard to imagine. Anyway, he's basically saying you
always go by the way it used to be, you don't go
by the current. So he disagrees with the ברייתא braita that said
you go by what it currently is when you're taking from the
dried on the undried. No, you go by the way it used
to be. But he's clear that we're talking about מעשר. ma'aser. Okay,
so he says ואי בתרומה גדולה עשר מאי עבידתיה? v'ee b'trumah gedola
eser mai avidteih? And if we're talking about
תרומה, trumah, what's this whole idea about ten over ninety? So obviously
we are not talking about תרומה. trumah. So we have a problem.
This position here of רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yosi
makes a lot of sense because he's saying you always go by
ten percent of what it used to be. It doesn't matter now
some are dried and some aren't and what you're taking from which,
you go by number which represents ten percent of what it used
to be. Okay, because number will always represent how they will all
originally. That makes sense, but what about the תנא קמא tanna kamma
that says you keep on switching it based on which way is
going to give you a larger measure? That's you can't do that
by מעשר. ma'aser. מעשר Ma'aser has to be an exact amount. So
the גמרא Gemara says, the גמרא Gemara has one other possibility up
its sleeve, אלא הכא בתרומת מעשר עסקינן. ela hacha b'trumat ma'aser askinan.
We're talking about תרומת מעשר. trumat ma'aser. תרומת מעשר Trumat ma'aser is
after you give the לויים Leviyyim their tenth, they give then a
tenth of their tenth to the כהן. Kohen. That's a תרומת מעשר.
trumat ma'aser. And there is a specific amount. It's not any amount
they want, it's exactly a tenth of their tenth. Okay, there's however
one הלכה halacha that the גמרא's Gemara going to say here which
is by תרומת מעשר, trumat ma'aser, although it's a tenth of a
tenth, you're allowed to be a little bit more flexible because it's
also called תרומה trumah and it goes to a כהן. Kohen. So
the same way with תרומה trumah you could have there's not really
a specific amount and you can be flexible, here although it's a
tenth, it means like rough a rough tenth. It's not an exact
tenth and you have a certain amount of flexibility in determining it.
Okay, so let's take a look.
ואבא אלעזר בן גומל
היא.
V'Aba Elazar
ben Gomel hee.
And this is אבא אלעזר בן גומל Aba Elazar ben Gomel from
some say גמלא, Gamla, דתניא, d'tanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braita,
אבא אלעזר בן גומל אומר, Aba Elazar ben Gomel omer, אבא אלעזר
בן גומל Aba Elazar ben Gomel says, ונחשב לכם תרומתכם. Venechshav lachem
trumatchem.
This is talking about the לויים Leviyyim when they give their תרומה,
trumah, so it is the תרומת מעשר. trumat ma'aser. The לויים Leviyyim
are giving a תרומה trumah to the כהנים, Kohanim, a tenth of
a tenth. It says it should be considered to you כתרומת גורן
וכמלאת היקב. kitrumat goren uch'mleat hayakev. It should be considered like the
תרומה trumah that the ישראל Yisrael gives from their grain, here's the
לוי, Levi, you're going to give a תרומה trumah from your tenth.
By the way, that's an interesting idea in general about somebody that's
receiving funds and getting צדקה tzedakah from elsewhere, do they have a
responsibility themselves to give צדקה? tzedakah? There's like an interesting תשובה tshuva
that רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein has about somebody that's like
ישיבה בחור, yeshiva bochur, whoever it is, that's getting supported by his
father-in-law and he wants to know if he has an obligation to
give מעשר כספים ma'aser kesafim on the very money that he's receiving
from his father-in-law. So you might want to ask his father-in-law that
question. But anyway, but the other point though is which is a
very nice point is that I forget the answer, I should check
it, but the other nice thing to think about that is that
on the one hand it's a little silly but on the other
why should, I mean my gosh you need funds stuff. On the
other hand it makes you more of a member of society. You're
not just a receiver, you're not just a taker, you're also a
giver.
And what'd they say in the poorest homes there was always a
צדקה tzedakah box.
Right, right, that's the whole idea, right.
And then contributing
to the building,
right, that's exactly the point, exactly. So even if it's not true
that there's always somebody less fortunate than yourself, I don't think that's
the point, I think the point is like you say, everybody counts
and everybody's contribution counts and what does it mean to be a
member of society and not just a נעבעך nebach who's receiving. So
anyway, so here you have it that even the לויים Leviyyim who
get their tenth give a tenth of their tenth. But it compares
their תרומה, trumah, their tenth of a tenth to the general תרומה
trumah and that's what we're going to focus on. בשתי תרומות הכתוב
מדבר, B'shtei trumot hakatuv medaber, talking about two types of תרומות. trumot.
אחת תרומה גדולה ואחת תרומת מעשר. Achat trumah gedola v'achat trumat ma'aser.
The normal תרומה trumah given by the ישראל Yisrael to the כהן
Kohen and the tenth of the tenth that the לוי Levi gives
to the
כהן. Kohen. כשם שתרומה גדולה... Keshem shetrumah gedola... באומד ובמחשבה, be-omed uv-machshava,
and the same way that normal תרומה truma can be taken by
אומד, omed, that's our key point here, by estimation, there's not even
a precise amount, you can just estimate, you can give whatever you
want, ובמחשבה, uv-machshava, which means you don't even have to, we'll talk
about מחשבה machshava in a minute, but for now it just means
you don't have to articulate it, you can just think in your
mind, I'm designating this as תרומה. truma. So therefore כך תרומת מעשר
ניטלת באומד ובמחשבה. kach trumas maaser nitalos be-omed uv-machshava. And therefore תרומת
מעשר trumas maaser is also given, can be given with אומד, omed,
with estimation, and with מחשבה, machshava, just mentally thinking about it. And
similarly, מה תרומה גדולה, ma truma gedola, says the גמרא Gemara here,
the גמרא's Gemara really adding this onto אבא גמליאל, Abba Gamliel, it's
not his original statement, I believe, מה תרומה גדולה בעין יפה אף
תרומת מעשר בעין יפה. ma truma gedola be-ayin yafa af trumas maaser
be-ayin yafa. So the same way תרומה גדולה truma gedola you can
sort of round up and have a rough estimate to give a
nice amount, and it's not a precise amount, here too as well.
So remember the גמרא's Gemara going back to the answer it gave,
which really it's a really problematic ברייתא, Braisa, make up your mind,
you either go by 10% now, 10% there, don't keep on switching
it, and the only common denominator of the ברייתא Braisa is we
always use a measure that's going to give more. But you can't
just say we like to give more by מעשר, maaser, right? מעשר
maaser is a precise amount. So the גמרא Gemara finds תרומת מעשר.
trumas maaser. תרומת מעשר trumas maaser is a tenth, but you have
a little latitude of how to say there's a tenth. באומד, be-omed,
you can estimate, you don't have to be precise tenth the same
way מעשר maaser is. And since you can estimate, so if you
have a question how should I measure it, based on now, based
on the way it was, am I taking the dried things, am
I not dried, the not dried on the dried, always use the
measurement that's going to mean you'll give more. Okay, get either the
volume or the number based on which way you'll give more, and
that you're allowed to do by תרומת מעשר. trumas maaser. תרומת מעשר
trumas maaser has that flexibility. Now תוספות Tosfos points out that there's
obviously a little bit of a problem. How do you compare תרומת
מעשר trumas maaser to תרומה? truma? תרומה truma can be given by
estimation because there's no amount at all, meaning not no, there's no
specific amount. So it's not like you can estimate the amount, it's
like there is no defined amount, so you can give whatever you
want to give. So how do you make that link to תרומת
מעשר trumas maaser where the תורה Torah says a tenth and you
say oh, so you can estimate the tenth and you can sort
of use, you know, whichever is the more generous measure? How do
you compare something that there's no amount to, to something that there
is an amount, to say oh you can give that amount by
sort of in sort of in a generous or by an estimated
measure? So תוספות Tosfos says okay, you're right, logically it's a problem,
but that's the גזירה שוה, gezeira shava, that's the way it's connected,
and that's what we learn out. But there is another answer. תוספות
Tosfos is always very insistent that the idea of 2% is rabbinic.
You know, because rabbis even say, they say 2% for a normal
person, a less generous person will give 1.6%,
a more generous person will give 2.5%. So they give like a
range and it sounds like it's all rabbinic and they say that
really תרומה truma you're יוצא yotzei even the smallest amount. חיטה אחת
פוטרת את הכרי. chita achas poteres es hakari. One grain of a
one grain, you know, exempts the entire amount, כרי, kari, pile. However,
there are those that disagree and say that there are two מצוות
mitzvos of תרומה. truma. That there's a מצוה mitzva to take the
תרומה truma which makes the, you know, separate the תרומה truma from
the grain, which makes the grain no longer טבל tevel and allows
you to eat from it, you still have to take מעשר maaser
and so on. But then there's a מצוה mitzva to give something
to the כהן. kohen. And to give something to the כהן kohen
means to give something substantial, not something trivial. Now of course, why
that's exactly defined by proportion of what you're taking, because you might
think it might defined by the absolute amount that you're giving, okay,
but some want to say that both are true. That the idea
of taking 2% is not purely rabbinic. That there's a biblical idea
of a tiny amount that exempts the כרי, kari, that exempts the
grain, but then there's also a biblical idea of giving the כהן
kohen something substantial and that translates into a certain percentage of what
you're giving, not something that's trivial. Now again, it's not a precise
percentage, roughly 2% give or take, you know, but there is a
sense of giving something of substance and that is part of the
תורה's Torah מצוה mitzva of תרומה. truma. That definitely fits nicely with
this גמרא Gemara that is basically is the פשט pshat of this
גמרא Gemara saying there is an amount of תרומה, truma, but you
have a certain amount of latitude in terms of estimating that amount.
And therefore trying to say the same thing about תרומת מעשר trumas
maaser as opposed to תוספות Tosfos that really says we're comparing תרומה
truma that has no amount and I mean no specific amount and
says oh no specific amount there, here even though there is a
specific amount you can sort of estimate
the guideline, in other words the guideline, ideally it should be 10%.
Right, it can be a minimum of...
Right by תרומה, truma, correct, the way it is. Correct. So now
we are saying
is something substantial if I'm just taking one
fruit? Then like the גמרא Gemara says, I'm being on that. But
that's the point, to give something
substantial.
Right, well that's the thing. Saying this approach means saying that substantial
is not defined by the absolute amount but by the relative to
what you're taking, which is, you know, can be obviously questioned.
Right, but
yes,
but what about the כזית? k'zayis? Wait a minute, isn't there an
absolute כזית? k'zayis?
It's at all or was it at all or big at all
or small at all. So the way I understood he was writing
was that the permit that whatever whatever you think at all of
it.
Right. Right. Well, that's a good point as well. So that's a
good point as well about the general our general desire to try
to get sort of precision where you were living in a clime
where pri measurements often were not really precise and where the תורה
Torah might not have and הלכה Halacha might not have demanded it,
like the whole question about, I'll give you a similar example of
יד סולדת בו, Yad Soledes Bo, how what's it considered like boiling
hot water or very hot water which is considered like cooking on
שבת Shabbos and other הלכות Halachot of יד סולדת בו. Yad Soledes
Bo. So you read you read the פוסקים Poskim and you'll see
specific numbers they try to figure out based on different גמרות, Gemaras,
110 degrees, 116 degrees, da da da da da. רב יהודה הרצל
הנקין Rav Yehuda Herzl Henkin says, what are you talking about? The
גמרא Gemara says how do you know if it's יד סולדת בו,
Yad Soledes Bo, you put your hand in it and you see
if you can keep your finger in it without yanking it away.
So that's how you know, don't tell me degrees, you stick your
hand in it. So that's the way הלכה Halacha wants us to
determine. It doesn't want us to sort of overly, which is funny
because normally so much of הלכה Halacha is about sort of quantifying
rules. But here it's not about quantifying the rule, it's about sort
of quantifying the measurement or the measurement and taking it out of
as you're right taking it out of the ability of the average
person to just measure for themselves, especially before you had thermometers and
whatnot. So that is presumably I have to read the I don't
I only glanced at the article but I'll look at it, but
I assume he's saying basically the same thing. If there's a שיעור
Shiur of an olive, so what for you is the normal size
of an olive? You don't have to go ahead and do a
world survey of olives. What for you are normal olives or in
your community or in your place? That's what you would use. Right.
And here so here this interesting because here nevertheless we are saying
that when it comes to normal מעשר Maaser even there you are
with your wheat you do have measuring things and in your farmer
or whatever go ahead and measure it. But by תרומת מעשר Terumas
Maaser we're sort of saying just guestimate the 10 percent. So it's
somewhat similar to those ideas. Yeah.
I'm forgetting the line but פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avos, אל תרבה לעשר
מאומד. Al tarbe l'aser me'umad. That's off of, yeah.
I don't know, help me. Yeah. Right to be but that's but
that's
exactly to give the right amount, don't give too much or too
little. Anyway here we're saying that for תרומת מעשר Terumas Maaser you
can guestimate. Okay, and therefore
therefore we use always the more generous measure. So let's go on.
And then it says ומינה Umina but from there we have that
that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer does not agree. The first opinion says
its תרומת מעשר Terumas Maaser give the more generous measure.
ומינה Umina אמר רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי אבא היה נוטל עשר גרוגרות
שבמקצוע כשם שאוכל בכל השנה. Amar Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yosi Abba haya
noteil eser gorgros shebe'iktza k'shem she'oiveil b'chol hano. Not true. He doesn't
agree. He says you don't just use the more generous measure and
you guestimate even if you're just talking about תרומת מעשר Terumas Maaser
which is how we're explaining it. My father always would take
ten dried dried dates for the ninety that were not dried. He
would not go by measure. He would go by number which would
represent a genuine 10 percent even though it was could be less
generous. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says according to him what's
he saying. אי אמרת כמות שהן אמרינן שפיר. Ee amart kemos shehein
amrinan shapir.
If you say by the way it used to be we understand
why you're taking ten dried figs over ninety not dried because that
represents an what originally were ten normal sized figs.
אלא אי אמרת כמות שהן בציר להו Ella ee amart kemos shehein
batshul'hu so you don't have enough. So the גמרא Gemara says okay
good. You got a פשט Pshat in the first half of the
ברייתא Braisa always use the more generous measure. But now let's look
at least at רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer statement. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says you take ten dried over the ninety not dried which means
you go by the way it used to be because if you
go by the way it is now ten dried figs do not
represent 10 percent as a volume
of a hundred not dried figs. So obviously at least רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer is going by the way it used to be and
that at least gives weight to the position that you go by
the way it used to be not by the way that it
was. Okay so at least we get some position from there. I'll
just say one more word about what the מחשבה Machshava means here.
I said before it just means sort of thought alone. If you
look take a look at the first line of תוספות Tosafot במחשבה.
b'Machshava. He says פירש בקונטרס Peireish bakuntres דף נה עמוד א Daf
Nun-He Amud-Aleph like four lines down five lines down in the wide
lines. פירש בקונטרס כדאמר בעלמא נותן עיניו בצד זה ואוכל בצד אחר.
Peireish bakuntres k'demar b'alma nosein eino b'tzad zeh v'ocheil b'tzad acher. That
you're at one side of the pile and you're looking at the
other side and you're eating from the side you're on שרצה לומר
משום דכתיב ונחשב שרי לאכול בלא הפרשה. she'ratza lomar mishum d'ksiv v'nechshav
sari l'echol b'lo hafrasha. You don't have to physically separate it ושרי
נמי בשתיקה. v'shari nami b'shtika. So תוספות Tosafot says that basically according
to רש"י Rashi it's two things. Number one you don't have to
physically take off the grain and number two is you don't even
have to verbally designate that section over there is תרומה Terumah or
תרומת מעשר. Terumas Maaser. You can just be thinking about it. Okay
and then תוספות Tosafot says well maybe not. Maybe that it doesn't
really mean that you don't have to maybe it doesn't mean maybe
במחשבה b'Machshava here does not go so far to mean you can
just think it. Maybe מחשבה Machshava here means you don't have to
physically separate the grain but you do have to say something. And
this then leads תוספות Tosafot to this question and I'm telling all
of you this because you know this from the beginning of זבחים
Zevachim right? זבחים Zevachim is all about if you have a thought
of שלא לשמו shelo lishmo and תוספות Tosafot and רש"י Rashi are
always taught to say oh thinking שלא לשמו shelo lishmo we really
mean you said something. It's not just what's going on in your
head. So תוספות Tosfos here as well says, when you say that
you can take תרומה terumah במחשבה, be-machshava, do you mean that you
can just think this section of grain is תרומה terumah or does
it mean you can say it, but you don't have to physically
separate? And maybe here as well מחשבה machshava means speech. So מחשבה
machshava is in contrast to action, but it doesn't just mean thinking.
It really would mean you would have to say it. So תוספות
Tosfos has this discussion whether you actually have to verbalize תרומה terumah
or not, but he brings it into this larger things that we've
had by קדשים Kodshim and לשמה, lishma, whether thinking it is what
does it or you actually have to verbalize. Okay, back to the
גמרא. Gemara. So now the, so now we have at least from
רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi Elazar berabi Yose the idea that you
go by the way it used to be. Okay, now back to
the גמרא, Gemara, five lines or six lines down on נ"ה, Nun-Hey,
כי אתא רב דימי, Ki ata Rav Dimi, when רב דימי Rav
Dimi came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi
Elazar, he said in the name of רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, שאני
גרוגרות, shani grogros, הואיל ויכול לשלקן ולהחזירן לכמות שהן. ho'il ve-yachol lesholkan
u-lehachziran le-chamus she-hein. Even רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי Rabbi Elazar berabi Yose
who says you go by the way it used to be, you
cannot prove that he, that he, that that's his general position. It
might be that this is specifically by dried figs. Why? Because dried
figs, you can go ahead and boil them and you can get
them back to their original state. You can basically, like we had
the, what was it, the dehydrated meat that gets the rain and
it gets bloated back up. Here you can rehydrate them. So here
he would say you never, you always look at them as the
way they were because they can always go back to being that
way. It does not prove that we always go by something's original
state. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. We're not done, we're going to
still try to prove it. תורמים תאנים על גרוגרות Tormin te'einim al
grogros במקום שרגילים לעשות, bemakom sheragilim la'asos, well actually we're not going
to try to prove it, we're just going to have a wrap
up discussion once we're talking about the whole thing about, about dried
and undried dates. So let's take a look. תורמים תאנים על גרוגרות.
Tormin te'einim al grogros. I did dates again, didn't I? Figs, sorry,
how many, all right, I keep on slipping. תורמים תאנים על גרוגרות,
Tormin te'einim al grogros, you can take from figs on dried figs
במקום שרגילים לעשות, bemakom sheragilim la'asos, where it is common that people
turn things into dried figs. Where it's a place where you regularly
process it and make it dried, you can take from non-dried figs
onto dried figs. תאנים במקום
שרגילים לעשות תאנים גרוגרות te'einim bemakom sheragilim la'asos te'einim grogros in a
place where they make the figs into dried figs. ולא גרוגרות על
תאנים, Velo grogros al te'einim, but you're not allowed to take dried
figs for the undried ואפילו במקום שרגילים לעשות תאנים גרוגרות, va'afillu bemakom
sheragilim la'asos te'einim grogros, even in a place where you do normally
process it. So what is going on here? We are not talking
here about how you measure the ten percent. You measure the ten
percent whatever we said before, a more generous way or always representing
the way it used to be, whatever you say. We're talking here
about the permissibility of whether you want, what are you going to
give the כהן? kohen? Are you going to give the כהן kohen
the תאנים, te'einim, the figs, or are you going to give him
the גרוגרות? grogros? What's the issue? The issue is figs taste better,
okay, but גרוגרות grogros last longer. So what does the כהן kohen
prefer? And there's generally going to be the normal assumption that we'll
see the גמרא Gemara will say is you'd rather give the כהן
kohen the nicer thing, okay, unless there's no כהן kohen around, then
you want to have take something that is going to last so
you can hold onto it until you find a כהן. kohen. All
right now again we're assuming the ten percent is done correctly however
you do the ten percent. Now the question is do you give
or if it's תרומה, terumah, right, I'm sorry, you're right we're talking
about כהן, kohen, thank you very much, my mistake, so we're talking
about, right, although the גמרא Gemara before whatever, right, whatever we're talking
about, either talking about תרומה, terumah, we're talking about the two percent
or we're talking about, but you're right the גמרא Gemara is going
to say כהן. kohen. So presumably we're talking about תרומה. terumah. So
the amount is done correctly, the percentage is done correctly, the question
is do you give figs or dried figs? Do you give תאנים
te'einim or גרוגרות? grogros? Let me look at this.
What I'm trying to understand is you can always get dry, so
give him the fresh one if it doesn't come.
That's exactly what the ברייתא braisa says. So what did the ברייתא
braisa say? The ברייתא braisa said you can give him the תאנים
te'einim if it's a place במקום שרגילים לעשות. bemakom sheragilim la'asos. So
if it's, if people do it, whether the כהן kohen himself does
it or anyway everybody in this town knows how to do it,
it's not a big deal, right, you take, you schlep the תאנים,
te'einim, you go you give it to somebody they'll take it. You
give him תאנים te'einim if it's easy to turn them into גרוגרות.
grogros. But you don't give him, you never give him גרוגרות grogros
even if that's a very common thing. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
is going to try to figure out what the logic of that
is. Is there a כהן kohen around or not around? So let's
take a look.
אמר מר, Amar Mar, תורמים תאנים על גרוגרות במקום שרגילים לעשות תאנים
גרוגרות, tormin te'einim al grogros bemakom sheragilim la'asos te'einim grogros, so you
can give him תאנים, te'einim, you know, the non-dried figs for the
גרוגרות grogros if they can normally get processed. So the גמרא Gemara
says במקום שרגילים אין, במקום שאינם רגילים לא. bemakom sheragilim in, bemakom
she'einam ragilim lo. It sounds like only if that they normally process
these things in this town and otherwise not. So what's the issue?
היכי דמי, Heichi dami, what's going on here? אי דאיכא כהן, Ei
de'ika kohen, if there's a כהן kohen available to give it to
him, so במקום שאינו רגיל אמאי לא, bemakom she'eino ragil amai lo,
why not give him a normal fig even if nobody, you know,
converts it into dried figs? If there's a כהן kohen around, give
him a fig, let him eat it now. You're not, it's not
your responsibility to preserve it for him. Just give him the fig
and anyway figs are nicer than dried figs. So why can't you
give him a fig even if nobody does process it? והתנן, Ve-hasnan,
we've taught in a משנה, mishna, במקום שיש כהן תורם מן היפה.
bemakom sheyesh kohen torem min hayaffe. If there's a כהן kohen around,
better to give him the nicer fruit even though it has less
longevity. Okay, so why does this ברייתא braisa say I can only
give the כהן kohein the figs if it would be easy for
him to convert it into dried figs. Why is it my responsibility
to worry? If I'm giving him the figs, then presumably it means
a כהן kohein is around. So what do I have to care
whether it can be converted or
not? What? That's not my responsibility if the משנה mishna says you
give the כהן kohein the nicer fruit, not the one of greater
longevity. So
אלא פשיטא ela peshita דליכא כהן. deleika kohein. Oh, so the only
way it makes sense is it means there's no כהן kohein around.
So if there's no כהן kohein around, so what's it telling you
to do? Don't be מפריש mafrish figs that are going to spoil,
be מפריש mafrish גרוגרות grogros unless,
unless it's a place where they make גרוגרות grogros in this town,
presumably meaning that then I can be מפריש mafrish figs if it's
going to be very trivial for me to then convert them to
גרוגרות. grogros. Okay, but presumably then wouldn't it be my responsibility if
there's no כהן kohein around, they're going to spoil, it doesn't matter
if my next door neighbor can make them into גרוגרות grogros if
they're sitting in my yard. Okay, but okay. You can be מפריש
mafrish if no כהן kohein around, you could be מפריש mafrish figs,
okay, but that's if it'll be easy to make them into גרוגרות
grogros and then presumably take care of making sure they're גרוגרות grogros
so that they'll last for the כהן. kohein. Fine. That's the first
line of the ברייתא. braisa. Now let's look at
the second line. So אימא סיפא, eima seifa, let's look at the
second line. ולא גרוגרות על תאנים, v'lo grogros al te'einim, but you
do not take dried figs over nice figs, אפילו במקום שרגיל לעשות
תאנים גרוגרות, afillu bimkom sheragil la'asos te'einim grogros, even if they normally
are processed here. So now one second, a minute ago you told
me take the figs because it's a place where they process it,
which means that it's easy to make them dried and because it's
desired to get them dried so they'll be longevity. And now you're
telling me don't take dried figs. Why not? So the גמרא Gemara
says דאיכא כהן, de'ika kohein, if there's no כהן kohein around, אמאי
לא, amai lo, why shouldn't I be taking dried figs? והתנן, vehatnan,
we taught in the משנה, mishna, מקום שאין כהן, makom she-ein kohein,
if there's no כהן kohein available, תורם מן המתקיים, toreim min hamiskayeim,
then you take your תרומה terumah not from the better quality but
from the stuff with greater longevity. So basically to, you know, sill
it, it's a very, I know, but it's a very, the ברייתא
braisa doesn't make sense. First it tells me take figs if it's
easy to convert them, which means that I want to get them
dried. And then it says don't take dried figs. So what the
heck is going on here? So the גמרא Gemara so it says,
well, we're talking very different cases. Is there כהן, kohein, not a
כהן? kohein? So אלא פשיטא דאיכא כהן, ela peshita de'ika kohein, so
the end of it where it says don't take dried figs must
be talking that there is a כהן kohein around. So that doesn't
make sense. רישא דליכא כהן סיפא דאיכא כהן? reisha deleika kohein seifa
de'ika kohein? How do you make, you know, the first part of
this ברייתא braisa is talking about that there's no כהן kohein and
it's advising me to make them dried or make, take it when
it's easy to get them dried, and the second part of the
ברייתא braisa is talking when there is a כהן kohein around and
it's telling me don't take them dried? So, you know, that's the
ברייתא? braisa? I know, but the whole point is, is this is
quite a sounding because it's basically the two halves of the ברייתא
braisa are telling you the exact opposite things, and the, the basic
point of, is there a כהן kohein around, not a כהן kohein
around, which makes the difference whether you do the first half of
the ברייתא braisa or the second half is completely missing. Okay, so
this ברייתא braisa is a big mess. So that's really what you
want me to say the ברייתא braisa means? The גמרא Gemara says
like Michal: Yeah, sure, why not? רישא דליכא כהן סיפא דאיכא כהן.
reisha deleika kohein seifa de'ika kohein. That's what the ברייתא braisa means.
The first half is saying that there's no כהן, kohein, so we're
saying take on the dried figs or take on figs that are
easy to convert to dried. The second part of the ברייתא braisa
is saying there is a כהן, kohein, so don't take on the
dried figs. So although the first half of the ברייתא braisa and
the second half basically contradict one another, we're going to say that
they're talking about exactly, exactly opposite scenarios. And that's why they don't
contradict. Now the גמרא, Gemara, רב פפא Rav Pappa makes an interesting
methodological point. So אמר רב פפא, amar Rav Pappa, says רב פפא,
Rav Pappa, שמע מינה, shma mina, I hear from the way you've
dealt with this ברייתא, braisa, דחקינן ומוקמינן מתניתין בתרי טעמי, dachkinan umokminan
matnisin bitrei ta'amei, you would rather have a משנה mishna mean two,
two different things, meaning have two completely different contexts, ולא מוקמינן בתרי
תנאי, velo mokminan bitrei tannai, rather than saying that it's a conflation
of two opinions of opposing תנאים tannaim that have been edited and
slapped together. Because the other way to have read the ברייתא braisa
is to say the first part, but basically the ברייתא braisa contradicts
itself. The first part says take figs if you can make them
dried, which basically means the goal is dried figs. The second part
says don't take dried figs, take fresh figs. So, you know, they,
it's basically the first half and second half contradict. Say that again?
So the first half says,
so because this is a thought
that, the first half says you can take figs if you can
make them dried, which means presumably the goal is dried figs, okay,
and the second part says don't take dried figs, only take fresh
figs. So what is going on? So the גמרא Gemara says, well,
we're talking very different cases. Is there כהן, kohein, not a כהן?
kohein? So רב פפא Rav Pappa says there was another way to
explain this ברייתא, braisa, maybe there's a מחלוקת תנאים machlokes tannaim and
two separate opinions are being slapped together. The one that says the
ideal is dried figs maybe feels there's always a goal of taking
things with longevity. The one that feels that the ideal is, the
second part of the ברייתא, braisa, that says not dried figs, normal
figs, is an opinion of a תנא tanna that says the goal
is always something that's better fruit. So maybe, you know, one is
an opinion that longevity is more, more important regardless yes כהן kohein
no כהן, kohein, the other is an opinion that maybe, you know,
the quality of fruit... is better. And one minute, so therefore, why
don't we just say that yes, there's a contradiction in this ברייתא,
braita, and we're not going to bother resolving it, it's two separate
opinions that were slapped together and that were edited together, because certainly
Rabbi did an editing job, he didn't do an authoring job, so
sometimes that happens, two different opinions get put together. So Rav Pappa
says we see as a methodological point we would rather assume that
it is one author and find a way to reconcile it by
saying a different context the beginning and the end is according to
כהן kohen available and not, rather than saying that there's different authors.
And I want to say something that this point that Rav Pappa
makes is basically the methodological point that informs the entire גמרא Gemara
and all of the
ראשונים. Rishonim. Because every single time and it's really the way almost
the ראשונים Rishonim are different than the גאונים. Geonim. Because think about
the activity of the ראשונים, Rishonim, the classic why we have these
huge תוספות, Tosafos, most of the time what a תוספות Tosafos is
doing is he's saying how come this גמרא Gemara says X and
the גמרא Gemara over there in the same discussion says Y. Now
the גאונים Geonim had a regular answer to those questions, you know
what their answer was? Okay, because this is גמרא מנחות Gemara Menachos
and that's גמרא בבא קמא Gemara Bava Kamma and the assumptions of
מנחות Menachos are not the same as assumptions of בבא קמא. Bava
Kamma. Basically תרי תנאי, trei tannai, okay, different opinions. Now, that might
be the more correct historical answer, but it does not make for
interesting learning, right? Because then every problem is just, oh, they were
just different opinions, different opinions thrown together, I don't have to bother
further, I don't have to invest too much intellectual energy, it's just
a lot of different voices, end of story. So
whereas the assumption תוספות Tosafos operates with, which is not necessarily correct
historically, but it's the assumption of how we're going to read the
text,
sort of from a learning and הלכה halakhic perspective, is we're going
to read the text as it's one voice, most at when we
can sustain that, and we're going to try to find some way
to reconcile. Even if that reconciliation means we have to say, well,
this is talking about this context, this was talking about nighttime, that
was talking about daytime, this was talking there is a כהן, kohen,
this was talking there not a כהן, kohen, but nevertheless, it helps
sort of, if you would, it's more interesting intellectually and it also
helps sharpen our ideas. Because if we're forced to say that this
law doesn't apply all this time and this doesn't always apply all
the time and it depends on the context, our ideas also get
sharpened in the process. And that really is the whole assumption of
how the learning operates. So this point that Rav Pappa makes, he's
making it as a methodological point. He's not saying historically this is
true. He's just saying if we have a choice how to interpret
the text, we'd rather interpret it as one voice and work to
reconcile it rather than interpret it as two voices. Okay, so that's
a very interesting little methodological point after all of the dates and
dried dates and whole dates, semi-dried dates. Actually it was the date
thing. We had figs and dried figs, etc. Okay.
So now you're going to have to reconcile why did Rabbi Eliezer
once call תאנים te'enim figs and the other time he called them...
okay, anyway, they are figs.
Exactly, exactly.
That's what you get by not living in Israel. Okay,
the fact that I can even recognize the difference between a date
and a fig when it's right in front of me... okay, but
anyway.
So what is the,
let's let the study go on
before
but that calls into question in a way the whole enterprise of
the, I mean puts in a different light I would
say, like enterprise of developing הלכה Halakha and the enterprise of the
גמרא. Gemara.
You mean because whether you're going to interpret things as just contradictory
voices or as,
right, as you say the difference between whether it's, maybe it's not
historically...
the גאונים Geonim were probably more historically correct. Yeah. But part of
what it means to codify a text and to make the text
authoritative is to say that we're going to sort of accept that
we're going to, we're going to try to read this text as
if it's speaking with one voice. Now sometimes you don't. Sometimes it's
very clear. In מנחות Menachos it's Rav Pappa and in בבא קמא
Bava Kamma it's Ravina, so you don't have to say they're the
same. But very often the contradictions are anonymous voice of the text,
the סתם Stam of the גמרא. Gemara. Now there too there were
different editors. There's not one person that wrote the סתם Stam of
the גמרא, Gemara, but the way that we sort of created as
canonized is by sort of that it becomes, at least for
תוספות, Tosafos, not for the...
now well I don't know because they were probably... that is a
good question. I mean Chaim Soloveitchik has written talked about that, that
the same was true at the time of the ראשונים Rishonim with
other types of legal texts in the secular world. Like there was
a whole enterprise going on at the same time תוספות Tosafos was
writing with canon law and
with Roman law which was the heritage of Europe and what they
were doing was exactly the same enterprise that תוספות Tosafos was doing
which was they were looking at all of the different statements and
rather than just assigning different authors, which was true there too, they
were basically trying to find ways to reconcile. So that was actually
called, there was a name for this process which was called the
dialectic process, which is the
constant, sort of the intentional search for contradictions for the desire to
find ways to reconcile it. Okay, not just, oh my god there's
a contradiction, what am I going to do, time to tragedy. You
actually go and you look for the contradictions with the goal to
try... find a way to reconcile and not to assign different authors.
What the גאונים *Geonim* was saying was probably more accurate historically. So
is that why he did it? Because what? So no, so first
of all there's a question did anybody influence anybody else and Haym
Soloveitchik has looked into this and cannot find any indication it was
acknowledged at the time that the same thing was going on in
the secular society, but there was no indication, there was no way
he could find any sort of you know points of influence. Like
do we have any indication that one influenced the other? But whatever
it was, that was what was going on.
But even the גאוני *Geonic* approach, you know, it doesn't end your
question because you still have to have a הלכה halacha. *Halachah* question.
Okay, it's very nice, if גמרא Gemara מנחות *Gemara Menachos* assumes one
thing, גמרא Gemara. בבא קמא *Gemara Bava Kamma* how do I פסקן
*Paskin*? מנחות *Menachos* or בבא קמא *Bava Kamma*? Okay so fine, sometimes
there're rules. You פסקן *Paskin* more by a גמרא Gemara *Gemara* where
it's the normal location. If you're having a נזיקין *Nezikin* issue then
you פסקן בבא קמא *Paskin Bava Kamma* over מנחות *Menachos*. If you're
having a מנחות *Menachos* issue you פסקן מנחות *Paskin Menachos* over בבא
קמא *Bava Kamma*. But it still doesn't tell you most of the
time how you're going to פסקן *Paskin*. It doesn't solve everything. Okay
but anyway, so it's not clear. The גאונים *Geonim*, it's sort of
like a difference between and we have to move on, בבלי *Bavli*
and ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*. Very often if there's a problem in the text
the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* gives an explanation which is more historically correct but
it's not as interesting. Like you know it might actually do because
it happened to have a different version of the text or some
type of a technical point or whatever it is, whereas the בבלי
*Bavli* you know is more removed historically and therefore you know more
sort of you know treats it right, conceptually and intellectually, rather than
having some type of a historical or textual explanation for it. So
all I can say is look, why do we פסקן *Paskin* like
I, we have to end this fascinating discussion right now but I'll
just say this, you know, if the points bother you though is
why do we פסקן *Paskin* that way if it's not what the
text originally meant, which is I assume what's underlying your question, then
the answer is yeah, but why do we פסקן *Paskin* the בבלי
*Bavli* and not the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi*? Maybe the ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* is closer
to the meaning of the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*. And at the end
of the day the הלכה halacha *Halachah* process is not that we
say what the משנה *Mishnah* originally meant or even what the תורה
Torah *Torah* originally meant. Okay what I'm saying is not so radical
like the רמב"ן *Ramban* says it, you know, whatever we had a
whole story about רב משה *Rav Moshe* and רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*
בבית מדרש *be-Beis Midrash* and so on, we'll talk about it another
time. But the idea that certain bodies like the תנאים *Tannaim* or
you know the חז"ל *Chazal*, the סנהדרין הגדולה *Sanhedrin HaGedolah* or or
certain texts like גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, משנה *Mishnah* get canonized and then
become authoritative and then the question stops being what did they originally
mean and becomes what are our principles of interpretation. Okay so that
was a nice little digression. Let's look at the משנה *Mishnah*. Okay
כל המנחות נילושות בפושרים *Kol hamenachos niochos befoshirin*. So all מנחות *menachos*
are are kneaded with lukewarm water. Now of course the גמרא gemara
*Gemara* never, yeah I know you're going to say that, the גמרא
gemara *Gemara* never tells you how you know you add water to
it. You know in the תורה torah *Torah* it only speaks about
שמן *shemen*, although the גמרא gemara *Gemara* does speak about, תורה *Torah*
does speak about you know baking certain מנחות *menachos* and then adding
the שמן *shemen*. So you can't exactly bake it unless you've added
something, okay, but the משנה *Mishnah* here assumes that you add water.
And of course since there's all issue that whether fruit juice of
which oil is included can cause חמץ chametz, *chometz*, and since the
תורה *Torah* is so much telling you don't make it חמץ chametz?
*chometz*, make it מצה matzah *matzah* and so on and actually two
things have to be חמץ chametz *chometz* as we've discussed, then the
משנה *Mishnah* assumes that water was an ingredient for all of them.
So all of them you would add lukewarm water. That is the
פשט pshat *pshat* of the, the assumption of the משנה *Mishnah*, although
as I mentioned to you it's interesting, the גמרא gemara *Gemara* never
tells you how we know you add water. I mean I just
sort of told you how logically you can figure it out.
And the תורה *Torah* never says it. The רמב"ם *Rambam* chooses to
read this משנה *Mishnah* of כל המנחות הנאפות *kol hamenachos hane'efos*, only
the ones that you bake. Okay the ones that you actually mix
with oil and basically do in a frying pan, there's no idea
of turning it into a bread-like substance and therefore there is no
water. Okay so but anyway our משנה *Mishnah* says כל המנחות נילושות
בפושרים *kol hamenachos niochos befoshirin*, all the מנחות *menachos* are are kneaded
with lukewarm water. Is there a Talmudic word for dialectics? Wait, יהודה
*Yohuda* asked. Dialectic? No, it's a ראשונים *Rishonim*. It's a, it's an
idea that came up in this, not ראשונים *Rishonim*, it was a
word that came up in the secular society in the time of
the ראשונים *Rishonim* and there is no גמרא gemara *Gemara* word for
it. When one of the בעלי תוספות *Baalei Tosfos* wants to refer
to it, actually he's being critical of it, he doesn't like quite
this new method of learning. I forget who it was, I think
it was רבי יהודה החסיד *Rabbi Yehuda HeHasid*. No, that's a later
word. He calls it הדיאלקטיקה של הגויים *Hadialectica shel hagoyim*.
So no there's no Talmudic word for it. Okay anyway כל המנחות
נילושות בפושרים *Kol hamenachos niochos befoshirin* ומשמרן שלא יחמיצו *umeshamem shelo yachmitzu*.
So all the מנחות *menachos* were kneaded with lukewarm water. Lukewarm water
so, you know,
as opposed to hot water.
It's like מים שלנו mayim shelanu *mayim shelanu* also.
Well that's the same idea. Hot water causes apparently the fermentation to
happen quicker, so you use lukewarm water so you are more on
top of preventing fermentation because we want it to be מצה *matzah*.
ומשמרן שלא יחמיצו *Umeshamem shelo yachmitzu* and you are very, you know,
and you're vigilant to make sure that it does not become חמץ
chametz. *chometz*. Like cold water, that too. ואם החמיצו שיריה *Veim hechmitsu
she'areha* and if it did become, did become חמץ chametz. *chometz*, like
you know you stopped working it for a while and it started
to ferment,
so ואם החמיצו שיריה *veim hechmitsu she'areha*, even if you let the
remnant become חמץ chametz, *chometz*, עובר בלא תעשה *over belo ta'aseh*. You
transgress a negative
commandment. So not only the simple sense of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*...
the rest. And now they're eating it, so it's no longer being
offered. Now they're eating it. Maybe now they can add water or
whatever and make it חמץ? chametz. No, even if you let the
remnant become חמץ, chametz. you are going to transgress. Now the question
is: how do you let the remnant become חמץ? chametz. I mean,
if you've already baked it, presumably unless you're a גבראכטס gebrochts person,
presumably, right, you cannot make something into חמץ chametz. after it's already
been baked. So presumably, it's a good question and I don't think
it's possible by the by the things like the frying pan and
the מחבת machavat or whatever you make it into חמץ. chametz. I
think there're two possibilities. Either you have the מנחת חוטא, minchat choteh,
which is just flour. So then afterwards you added water and you
let it become חמץ. chametz, Or the מנחת סולת, minchat solet, the
simple מנחה, mincha, right, which is just which is just basically dough
is something where you have a real challenge because you make it
dough, and now you have to bring it and you can't let
it become חמץ, chametz? but it's just dough. It hasn't been baked
yet. So you gotta be sort of like rushing, take the קומץ,
kometz, burn it, whatever, and then right after it gets burned, what
are you going to do with it? You gotta like throw it
in an oven to prevent it from becoming חמץ. chametz. So that's
the one that it's a real challenge to prevent it to becoming
חמץ. chametz, And even after you've offered the קומץ, kometz, you have
to make sure that the the remnant does not become חמץ.
chametz. Do the כהנים kohanim eat it like then and there or
do they wait until the end of the day?
No, they can eat it then and there, they better throw it
in an oven,
even though the rest of it's going to become
חמץ.
chametz, Does that go with the משמשו? mashmesho?
Yeah, keep kneading it. I mean, usually right, keep kneading it. Or,
if you stop kneading it for a while, keep your eye on
it to make sure it hasn't started crusting, whatever then you would
see that it became חמץ. chametz But actually, but then you've been
over already. So yeah, so but you probably see when it's about
to. Like keep your eye on it and you see it's starting
to ferment, you know, the crusting or whatever is beginning to happen,
then start working it again. Okay, but really it basically means just
keep on working it.
Okay, but I'm trying to also not understand they said warm water,
they don't mean to the exclusion of cold water, does that mean
even warm water?
I believe so, yeah.
Right, because I would say that if you're really worried about חמץ,
chametz. then לכתחילה l'chatchila say that you should use cold water.
Yeah, I'm not sure. I'm not sure about the whole water. I
have to check. Meaning I remember that like you know obviously the
מים שלנו by making מצה and so on, and I have to
check what if there's this discussion about the the cold water issue.
I just don't maybe there's a method of using
different temperatures or whatever.
Right. Okay, so let's go on. שנאמר, she'ne'emar, as the פסוק pasuk:
says, how do you know there's an איסור issur of making of
allowing it to become חמץ? chametz, There's a פסוק: pasuk כל המנחה
אשר תקריבו לה' לא תעשה חמץ. kol hamincha asher takrivu l'Adonai lo
te'aseh chametz. Any מנחה mincha do not make it חמץ. chametz. דחייב
על לישתה ועל עריכתה ועל אפייתה. d'chayav al lishata v'al arichata v'al
afiyata. As the גמרא gemara, says, because the word does not say
don't bake it חמץ, chametz but don't make it חמץ. chametz. Any
part of the process that was a making of it that allowed
it to ferment, you're חייב. chayav. So if you kneaded it after
it was after it had fermented, so you're now kneading חמץ, chametz,
or you are עריכה aricha which is like putting it in the
in the mold, or you're baking it, all of those are part
of making it, and if it's חמץ chametz you have transgressed making
it חמץ. chametz. It's not just the baking of it חמץ, chametz.
it's any action that is making it חמץ.
chametz. Oh, does that mean while it became חמץ chametz. in the
very beginning, and then I do this and then that, I'm also
חייב chayav each...
Yes, that is exactly what it is saying. Any continued making, even
though it was already חמץ. chametz. So but I didn't do anything
else. Any continued making you are transgressing, you are in the process
of making it while... So it's not just don't let it become
חמץ, chametz don't make something out of חמץ chametz. and you are
continuing to make it out of חמץ. chametz, Okay, so let's take
a look at the גמרא. gemara מנא הני מילי? m'na hani milei?
Where do you know this, not just that there's a prohibition, but
that the prohibition applies to the remnant of the מנחה, mincha, to
the שיירים? shirayim? אמר ריש לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, אמר קרא, amar
kra, the פסוק pasuk says: לא תאפה חמץ, lo te'afeh chametz, you're
not allowed your מנחה mincha to become חמץ. chametz, And then the
end of the פסוק pasuk is: חלקם נתתי אותה מאשי. chelkam natati
otah me'ishay. I have given you my portion from the fire. So
the גמרא gemara reads it by putting the comma in a different
place. לא תאפה חמץ חלקם. lo te'afeh chametz chelkam. Do not let
the portion of the כהנים kohanim become חמץ. chametz, So even the
remnant, even the שיירים shirayim cannot become חמץ. chametz, אפילו חלקם לא
תאפה חמץ. afilu chelkam lo te'afeh chametz. Even their portion cannot become
חמץ. chametz, So the גמרא gemara says: האי להכי הוא דאתא? hai
l'hachi hu d'ata? Is that what you need the פסוק pasuk for?
המיבעי ליה לכדתניא. hamibayei leh l'chadetanya. You need it for a more
basic thing like what's found in a
ברייתא. braita. Oh, they almost had a big accident there. לא תאפה
חמץ. lo te'afeh chametz. מה תלמוד לומר? mah talmud lomar? What's meant
by the verse "Do not bake it חמץ"? chametz, הלוא
כבר נאמר בצו, halo kvar ne'emar b'Tzav, but it already says in
ויקרא, Vayikra, לא תעשה חמץ, lo te'aseh chametz, do not make it
חמץ. chametz And here we're going to focus on the difference between
make and bake. Make means as the משנה said any part of
the process. Bake is just baking. So why did the תורה have
to say baking if it already said making and making is more
inclusive, it's any part of the
process? לפי שנאמר לא תעשה חמץ, lefi she'ne'emar lo te'aseh chametz, because
it says don't make it חמץ, chametz, יכול לא יהיה חייב אלא
על אחת על כולן. yachol lo yiheye chayav ela al achat al
kulan. Maybe I only transgress one prohibition. If it just said don't
make it חמץ, chametz so if I did five things wrong, I
kneaded it as חמץ, chametz, I did the עריכה aricha as חמץ,
chametz I baked it as חמץ, chametz, maybe I've only transgressed one
prohibition: making it. How do I know that every different act is
a different transgression?
למה יצאת, lamah yatzas, why was it singled out? להקיש אליה, lehakish
aleha, to connect to it, meaning to use it as a model
and to say מה אפייה מיוחדת שהיא מעשה יחידי וחייב עליה בפני
עצמה, mah afiyah meyudedes she'hi ma'aseh yechidi v'chayav aleha bifnei atzmah,
the same way baking is a is a stage in the process,
a specific stage in the process, and you transgress for doing that
stage of baking, אף אני אביא לישתה ועריכתה וכל מעשה יחידי, af
ani avi lishtah v'arichatah v'chol ma'aseh yechidi, I will bring any significant
stage of the process, which is the kneading, the sort of putting
it in the form, and any other individual stage, לאתויי קיטוף, le'asuyei
kituf, which includes the slapping, right when you make dough, you sort
of like slap the bread in order to smooth it out or
whatever, שהוא מעשה יחידי וחייב עליה בפני עצמן, she'hu ma'aseh yechidi v'chayav
aleha bifnei atzman, that is a stage of the
process and you transgress by itself. Is that what it's for, is
doing the air, and you get and you're and you transgress by
itself? So the ברייתא braisa here is saying why do I need
two פסוקים, psukim, one that says don't make and one that says
don't bake, because it is true that to tell you that the
same way baking you're חייב chayav for that as a lone act,
so even if you did a whole process of acts, every separate
act would be a separate transgression. Okay, the same way baking is
a separate transgression, it's not all one making of חמץ, chametz, every
separate act has its own significance and is a separate transgression. Okay,
so that's why I need the פסוקים psukim for, not to tell
me that the איסור issur of חמץ chametz, applies to the remnant
of the מנחה. mincha. So how do you know it? So the
גמרא Gemara says no, one minute. You can learn both out. The
גמרא Gemara says אמר מחלקם קאמינא. amar me'chelkam ka'amina. Where the problem
now? It depends, we need the פסוק pasuk to tell me you're
חייב chayav for each stage, not to tell the remnant מנחה. mincha.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, no, no, our דרשה drasha wasn't
from the basic. The basic פסוק pasuk. you're right, is telling you
that there are a prohibition for each act etc. We are דרשנינג
darshening from the juxtaposition of the word חלקם. chelkam. It says don't
make חמץ, chametz, לא תאפה
חמץ חלקם. lo te'afeh chametz chelkam. So the fact that the word
חלקם chelkam was juxtaposed means don't even bake the remnant חמץ chametz,
and that's what we're learning it from, not from the whole פסוק.
pasuk So the גמרא Gemara says אימא לכולה להכי הוא דאתא, eima
l'chulah l'hachi hu de'asa, maybe the whole פסוק pasuk. is just to
tell you the prohibition of the remnant and not this idea of
that you're חייב chayav for each stage? So the גמרא Gemara says
no, אם כן ליכתוב, im kein lichtov, then say it explicitly. חלקם
לא תאפה חמץ, chelkam lo te'afeh chametz, which you know, their portion
don't bake חמץ, chametz it would just be very clear the תורה's
only concerned about focusing on the portion of the כהנים, kohanim, the
remnant. מה לא תאפה חמץ חלקם, mah lo te'afeh chametz chelkam, why
does it first say don't bake חמץ chametz, and then tag on
the word חלקם, chelkam, which as we know, according to פשט is
really part of the next phrase, but anyway, why is it written
this way? To tell you two things. שמעת מינה תרתי, shamas minah
tarti, to tell you first of all there's a general principle, לא
תאפה חמץ, lo te'afeh chametz, and that allows us to say that
you're חייב chayav for every stage, and then there's another word juxtaposed
חלקם chelkam to tell you you're חייב chayav for the כהנים's kohanim
portion as well, even if you've already done the קומץ, komets, if
you bake the חמץ, if you do the כהנים kohanim portion you're
also חייב. chayav.
So what I get out of that is let's say you baked
it as חמץ, you're over, but I can still eat it if
it's חמץ, even if I can't eat it as חמץ, it's שיריים,
shirayim, right?
But why you can't be מכתיר חמץ maktir chametz and you can't
make it חמץ, you're in איסור issur of אכילה achilah of חמץ
and of שיריים. shirayim. That is definitely discussed later in the גמרא,
Gemara I'm not remembering the סוגיא sugya offhand, but you're right, in
the פסוקים psukim it's not there. I don't,
but it definitely is discussed, I just don't remember offhand, but it's
not in the פסוק. pasuk Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, ואימא אפייה דפרט רחמנא לחייב חדא אינך לחייב חדא אכולהו, v'eima
afiyah d'parat rachmana l'chayev chada inach l'chayev chada a'kul'hu, how do you
know to do to, fine, we're done with חלקם. chelkam. Now we're
going to figure out this idea of being חייב chayav at each
stage. So the גמרא says one minute, what makes you say that
we use baking as a model and say the same way baking
you're חייב chayav for, you're חייב chayav for every stage by itself?
Why don't we say there are two prohibitions: one prohibition of baking
and one prohibition of לא תעשה lo ta'aseh of all the other
processes? And all the other processes you're חייב chayav one prohibition. So
if you go ahead and you don't actually do the baking but
you do the kneading and the this and the this and the
this, it's all one prohibition of make, and baking is a separate
prohibition. What allowed you to use baking as a model to say
you're חייב chayav for each stage rather than to treat these as
two separate prohibitions: baking by itself and the rest of the makings?
אפייה לחלק? afiyah l'chalek? Right,
well that's basically the question exactly. Okay, the גמרא says okay,
one minute, where am I?
מה לא תאפה חמץ חלקם? mah lo te'afeh chametz chelkam? ואימא אפייה
דפרט רחמנא לחייב חדא, v'eima afiyah d'parat rachmana l'chayev chada, so baking
which is explicit, that's a separate prohibition and you get for just
baking, אינך, inach, all the other processes, לחייב חדא אכולהו, l'chayev chada
a'kulhu, there's only one transgression. As that separate prohibition? So it says
no because that goes against our general principle. Here's our general hermeneutic
principle: משום דהוי דבר שהיה בכלל ויצא מן הכלל ללמד, mishum d'havei
davar she'hayah b'khlal v'yatza min ha'khlal lilmed, something that was originally included
in a general category, don't make, making included everything including baking, and
then it was taken out of that category to tell you a
particular
הלכה. לא ללמד על עצמו יצא, lo lilmed al atzmo yatza, it's
not just telling you a הלכה about it
itself. it's come to tell you something about the whole category. So
this is one of our classic hermeneutic principles for those that say
it in the morning, you say it every morning, ר' ישמעאל, Rabbi
Ishmael, which means okay, we're not going to say baking is special.
We're going to say baking represents everything that was in that group.
Okay, and it's used as a model for everything in that group.
So it's a process and therefore you're חייב chayav for the baking
process and you're חייב chayav for each process individually. Okay, the גמרא
says one minute, ואימא, veima, you're telling me hermeneutic principles, I got
another hermeneutic principle that you could have used. Why don't we say
like this: לא תעשה כלל, lo taaseh klal, the פסוק pasuk that
says don't make it חמץ, that's a general statement. לא תאפה פרט,
lo teafeh prat, do not bake is a limiting statement. כלל ופרט
אין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט. klal uprat ein baklal ela ma shebaprat.
So rather than reading it as something that's taken out of a
group and now represents the whole group, say no, no, no, there
was a general פסוק pasuk don't make, but now another פסוק pasuk
said don't bake. Bake is an explicating what make means. It's a
כלל ופרט klal uprat and really the whole prohibition is just for
baking. אפייה afiyah in, just baking, מידי אחרינא לא, midei achreina lo,
nothing else.
Then we'd say well just baking then what? We'd say the same
thing.
What? What? Okay, but that's always the question about כלל ופרט. klal
uprat. Okay, so אמר רב אבטוריקי, amar rav aftoriki, so Rabbi Aftoriki
says, interesting name, משום דהוי כלל ופרט המרוחקים זה מזה. mishum dehavei
klal uprat hamiruchakim zeh mizeh. You can't do that. They're not juxtaposed.
Right, the פסוק pasuk one פסוק pasuk is in צו, Tzav, and
the other פסוק pasuk is in ויקרא. Vayikra. In ויקרא Vayikra it
says לא תעשה, lo taaseh, in I'm sorry, in ויקרא Vayikra it
says לא תעשה, lo taaseh, in צו Tzav it says לא תאפה.
lo teafeh. You can't make a כלל ופרט klal uprat when they're
like five פרשיות parashiot away from one another. דכל כלל ופרט המרוחקים
זה מזה אין דנין אותו בכלל ופרט. dechol klal uprat hamiruchakim zeh
mizeh ein danin oso beklal uprat. When they're not juxtaposed you cannot
do כלל ופרט. klal uprat. The גמרא now is going to get
onto this little digression about hermeneutics. So, מתיבי רב אדא בר אבא,
masvi rav ada bar abba, so Rav Ada bar Abba asks, אמרי
לה כדי, amrei lei kadi, and some say כדי, kadi, רש"י Rashi
says כדי kadi either means there was somebody by the name of
Kaddi, but כדי kadi in the גמרא means for naught. So Rabbi
Yoel says like it means nobody in particular said it. It was
just like an anonymous statement, it was a common statement, anonymous, right.
So what did he say? One minute, we've just got to focus
now. דכלל deklal so he says וכלל ופרט המרוחקים זה מזה אין
דנין, veklal uprat hamiruchakim zeh mizeh ein danin, is it really true
that we do not interpret it when they are when they are
far away, we don't make a
כלל ופרט? klal uprat? והתניא, veatanya, so you see that we do.
And here we get to קדשים, Kodshim, back to קדשים. Kodshim. ושחט
אתו במקום אשר ישחט את העלה לפני ה' חטאת הוא. veshachat oso
bimkom asher yishchat haolah lifnei Hashem chatas hu. So this is about
the goat that the נשיא nasi would bring when he brings his
special חטאת chatas and it says you slaughter it where you would
slaughter the עולה olah before God. So היכן עולה נשחטת בצפון? heichan
olah nishcheta batzafon? So where is the עולה olah slaughtered? We know
in the north. אף זה בצפון. af zeh batzafon. So this is
in the north. So fine, we know the חטאת chatas of a
נשיא nasi is in the north. Now, this is not the end
of the ברייתא, brayta, then it goes on. וכי אנו מכאן למדין,
vechi anu mikan lomedin, do we learn from this that the חטאת
chatas is in the north? והלא כבר נאמר vehalo kvar neemar later
on in צו, Tzav, במקום אשר תשחט העלה תשחט החטאת, bimkom asher
tishachat haolah tishachat hachatas, where you slaughter the עולה olah you slaughter
the חטאת? chatas? So again, one פסוק pasuk in ויקרא Vayikra by
the a חטאת chatas of a נשיא nasi says you slaughter in
the north. There's another פסוק pasuk. in צו Tzav מרוחקים זה מזה
miruchakim zeh mizeh says every חטאת chatas you do in the north.
Okay, and now let's see what the ברייתא brayta does with it.
הלמה יצא, halama yatza,
why was the goat of a נשיא nasi singled out? לקובעו, lekovo,
to establish it, to say it must be this way. אם לא
שחט אתו בצפון פסלו. im lo shachat oso batzafon psalo. That if
you don't do it in the north you've invalidated it, that's why
it's said again by the goat of a נשיא nasi to tell
you it's not just לכתחילה lechatchila to do the slaughtering of north,
but if it's not done it's invalidated. אתה אומר לכך יצא, atah
omer lekach yatza, you're saying that's why it was singled out. או
אינו אלא שזה טעון צפון ואין אחר טעון צפון. o eino ela
shezeh teun tzafon veein acher teun tzafon. Maybe it's to tell you
that only the goat of a נשיא nasi is in the north,
and no other חטאת chatas is in the north. So, תלמוד לומר,
talmud lomar, so there's a third פסוק. pasuk ושחט את החטאת במקום
העלה, veshachat es hachatas bimkom haolah,
you slaughter the חטאת chatas in the place of the עולה. olah.
זה בנין אב לכל חטאות, zeh binyan av lechol chataos, it's telling
you all sin offerings שטעונות צפון sheteunos tzafon are in the north
and you cannot just say just this one. Okay, so this is
where the ברייתא brayta learned out that you the חטאת chatas is
in the north and then if you don't do it it's מעכב.
meakev. What's interesting to us is the הוה אמינא hava amina of
the ברייתא brayta that said maybe only the חטאת chatas of the
נשיא nasi is in the north. How could you say that? We
just quoted a פסוק pasuk. that says by generally by a חטאת
chatas you slaughter the חטאת chatas with the עולה. olah. So it
must be the ברייתא brayta is suggesting to read it as a
כלל ופרט. klal uprat. Read the general statement in צו Tzav as
a כלל, klal, read the specific statement in ויקרא Vayikra as a
נשיא's nasi חטאת chatas as a פרט. prat. Even though so even
though they're far away and to limit it just to the example
of the נשיא. nasi. So that's the גמרא's proof. The גמרא says
טעמא דכתב רחמנא ושחט את החטאת, taama dechasav rachmana veshachat es hachatas,
is because it says a third פסוק. pasuk הא לאו הכי, ha
lav hachi, had that not been the case, הוה אמינא, hava amina,
you'd think, שזה טעון צפון, shezeh teun tzafon, that the goat of
the נשיא nasi requires north, ואין אחר טעון צפון, veein acher teun
tzafon, and no other חטאת. chatas.
Why is that? It says a whole big פסוק pasuk, over there
in צו. Tzav. מאי טעמא, mai taama, what's the reason? לאו משום
דהוי כלל ופרט, lav mishum dehavei klal uprat, it must be because
it's a כלל ופרט. klal uprat. ואף על גב דמרוחקים זה מזה
דנין אותו, veaf al gav demiruchakim zeh mizeh danin oso, and even
though one is in ויקרא Vayikra and one is in צו. Tzav.
You see you can interpret it. So the גמרא says look, this
ברייתא baraisa assumes you could have, had it not had another פסוק,
pasuk it would have read it as the כלל ופרט. klal u-prat.
So the גמרא said no, that's not true. מתקיף רב אשי, Matkif
Rav Ashi, I'll prove to you that's not what's going on there.
האי כלל ופרט הוא? Hai klal u-prat hu? It's not a כלל
ופרט, klal u-prat, it's the opposite! פרט וכלל הוא! Prat u-klal hu!
If you really were reading it that way, the first פסוק pasuk
in ויקרא Vayikra is the specific one about the goat of the
נשיא. Nasi. The next פסוק in צו Tzav is the general one,
all חטאת chatas is slaughtered in the north. So if we're really
reading it by פרט וכלל prat u-klal principles, what happens when the
פרט prat comes first and the כלל klal comes after? Is that
ונעשה הכלל מוסיף על הפרט? ve-na'aseh ha-klal mosif al ha-prat? So the
כלל klal is adding, ואיתרבו להו כל מילי, ve-israbu lehu kol mili,
everything would be included. So when we're saying this ברייתא, baraisa, it's
not כלל ופרט klal u-prat principles. If that was what was going
on, it would have been reversed. אלא, Ela, what's going on in
this ברייתא? baraisa? תנא אותו קשיא ליה. Tanna oso kashya leh.
He's bothered with the word of אותו. oso. It says ושחט אותו
ve-shachat oso by the goat of נחשון, Nachshon, by the goat of
the נשיא. Nasi. הכי קאמר, Hechi ka'amar, and this is what he's
saying: או אינו אלא שזה טעון צפון ואין אחר טעון צפון? O
einu ela she-zeh taun tzafon ve-ein acher taun tzafon? Maybe only the
חטאת chatas of a נשיא Nasi gets north and nothing else? Not
because of כלל ופרט. klal u-prat. Why would I think just the
one of the נשיא? Nasi? דכתיב רחמנא אותו, De-chtiv rachmana oso, because
it said it, which means only it. Okay, and therefore that's why,
that's why I would have thought to have read it that way.
It's not based on כלל ופרט, klal u-prat, it's based on the
word of אותו, oso, and we are repeating our principle that we
do not say כלל ופרט klal u-prat when they are far away
from one another.